<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Lent-sermon preached in the cathedral church at Norwich upon a Shrove Svnday by Robert Seppens ...</title>
            <author>Seppens, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59213</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2559_VARIANT</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33864</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13585567</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13585567</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100527</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59213)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100527)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1048:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Lent-sermon preached in the cathedral church at Norwich upon a Shrove Svnday by Robert Seppens ...</title>
                  <author>Seppens, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.C. for William Oliver ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lenten sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100527:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A <hi>LENT-Sermon</hi> Preached in the Cathedral Church AT NORWICH, UPON A <hi>SHRO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDAY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY <hi>ROBERT SEPPENS</hi> Rector of <hi>Hingham</hi> in <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>M. C.</hi> for <hi>William Oliver,</hi> Bookſeller, in the Market-Place in <hi>Norwich.</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100527:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100527:2"/>
            <head>To the very much Honoured Sir <hi>Philip Woodhouſe</hi> Baronet.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Have profan'd your name ſo far, as to prefix it to this trifle, not becauſe I think it worthy of your ſight or acceptance, but becauſe it may be ſubſervient to my deſign; and my deſign in this Paper is to give ſome check to the Luxury of this Age, and to retrieve the Antient Diſcipline of the Church concerning Maceration of the Body, and to effect that, to recommend the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of great St. <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle, and other Apoſtolick men who were followers of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> even as he was of Chriſt. It was a celebrious Sermon of <hi>Seneca,</hi> though a Heathen man, <hi>non ideo natus ſum ut mancipium fiam corporis,</hi> I was not therefore born that I might become a ſlave of the Body; which you have ſomwhere illuſtrated by a Divine Poem, but made more illuſtrious by your Divine Life; for though you and your Anceſtors have been renown'd for your Hoſpitality and Noble Houſe-keeping, yet I dare avouch it, there is no Aſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick living uſes more moderation and abſtinence, in eating and drinking than your ſelf. The Aſcetick is in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="tcp:100527:3"/>forc'd to it by the Rules of his Order, but you do it out of pure choice. What <hi>Minucius Foelix</hi> ſaith of the firſt Chriſtians, they did <hi>vivere grandia,</hi> live great things; I may ſay of you; you do <hi>vivere grandia,</hi> you live above the rate of the vulgar, you live above the rate of perſons of your own Rank and Quality; you live above the rate of us Eccleſiaſticks. There is no Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtick of us all ſpends more time in Holy Reading, and takes more pains in ſearching into the deep things of Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy than your ſelf. There are more great things of your life I could mention, as your great Loyalty to your Prince, your immenſe Charity to all Diſſenters from you, your profound humility; but I am afraid I ſhall treſpaſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Modeſty, as St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> the holy Martyr in one of his genuine Epiſtles ſays, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they which commend me ſcourge me. I ſhall add no more but only this petition, which is, that you would par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don my preſumption in uſing your name, and give me leave to ſubſcribe my ſelf what I really am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Moſt Honoured Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your humble Servant <hi>Robert Seppens.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100527:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON ON</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 COR. ix. 27.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But I keep under my body and bring it into ſubjection.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am come the ſecond time upon a <hi>Shrove-Sunday</hi> (I cannot tell whether by chance or choice) to perform the Pulpit-Office of the day; and I know not how I ſhould better manage that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, than by minding you of the approaching Faſt of <hi>Lent,</hi> nor how better to diſpoſe you for that, than by preſenting you with a Map of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Auſterities. If I ſhould propound unto you this day the example of Chriſts forty daies faſt in the Wilderneſs; you would ſay happily, that was Miraculous: <hi>quis ſicut Dominus Deus noſter?</hi> who is like unto the Lord our God? who by the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100527:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>power of his Divine Nature could ſupport the frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his Human: well therefore we preſs not Chriſts example, but <hi>humanum dicimus propter infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem,</hi> we ſpeak after the manner of man becauſe of your infirmities. I bring you the example of a man, a mere man, that was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the ſame Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we are of, to direct you, and encourage you to the Chriſtian Combats with your fleſh in the following time of <hi>Lent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether St. <hi>Paul</hi> or the other Apoſtles kept the Faſt of <hi>Lent</hi> formally, I know not, there are ſome in the world bold to avouch it: but if they did not, this I am ſure of, they practiſed the duties of <hi>Lent</hi> preciſely; and if we could but once agree about them, we ſhould never fall out about the time. If it once be granted that the duties of <hi>Lent</hi> be lawful, and needful, ſurely there muſt be a time allowed them: for <hi>omnia tempus habent,</hi> there is a time for all things under the Sun. And that the Apoſtles obſerved the duties of <hi>Lent</hi> ſtrictly, St. <hi>Paul</hi> is my Record in this place, who in the end of this Chapter Exhorting the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend and ſtrive for the heavenly prize of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, by a double example ſhews after what manner they ſhould do it.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. ix. 25.</note> Firſt by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the <hi>Pugills,</hi> and <hi>Pancratiaſts</hi> in the <hi>Graecian</hi> Combats. <hi>There every man,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And if they keep a ſtrict regiment over their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to obtain a poor Silver Game, what ſhould we
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100527:4"/>do for the Golden prize of Salvation? And then by his own example derived from theirs; <hi>I therefore ſo run, not as uncertainly, ſo fight I not as one that beats the air. But I keep under my body and bring it into ſubjection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So my Text (you ſee) contains <hi>officium quadra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſsimale</hi> a <hi>Lent</hi> duty practiſed by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> or to keep our ſelves to the Metaphor of fighting, a Chriſtian Combat, (as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith) <hi>Quadrageſsima die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus implendum,</hi> to be fought in daies of <hi>Lent,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are four things to be obſerved.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Pugil,</hi> the Champion, I.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Antagoniſta,</hi> the adverſary he fights againſt, his body.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Modus pugnandi,</hi> the manner of his fighting, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I keep it under.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Victoria,</hi> the victory he gets by this manner, I bring it into ſubjection.</p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt, The <hi>Pugil,</hi> or the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion, St. <hi>Paul,</hi> I. St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> thinks that St. <hi>Pauls</hi> name was changed from <hi>Saul</hi> to <hi>Paul, quia ex ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbo factus eſt modicus. Paulum enim modicum eſt,</hi> becauſe at his firſt Converſion he was turned from a proud man to be an humble man, for <hi>Paulus</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies <hi>little</hi> in Latin. Whether that was the true cauſe of the mutation of his name or no I know not. But that St. <hi>Paul,</hi> was <hi>Paulus</hi> little in his own eyes, appears by this: That even now when he had made a progreſs in Chriſtianity, when he had ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to a great degree of ſanctity, yet he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100527:5"/>haved not himſelf proudly, not preſumptuouſly, not ſecurely, he accounts not himſelf a Conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, but a fighter ſtill. <hi>So fight I.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> was now a Saint of great perfection, and by looking upon the ſtate of vulgar Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; he might have juſtified himſelf by negatives as the Phariſee did, <hi>Lord I think thee, I am not as other men.</hi> He was Spiritual, when they were Carnal, he was ſtrong when they were weak, he was a great proficient, when they were but inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pients in the School of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>He was now an Apoſtle, in journeying often, in painfulneſs and wearineſs. In planting of the Goſpel he had laboured more abundantly than all. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> xv. 10.</p>
            <p>Not more abundantly than any one, but more abundantly than all together: <hi>Noviſsimus in ordine, primus in meritis,</hi> though he was laſt in order called to the Apoſtleſhip, yet he was firſt in labours, <hi>quia extremus licet, plus omnibus laboravit,</hi> though laſt, yet he laboured more than all.</p>
            <p>He was now a glorious Confeſſour in bonds and impriſonment. It was given to him not only to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve but to ſuffer alſo for the name of Chriſt. He had gone through various dangers, perils at Sea and perils at Land: Who of us could have endured half ſo much abroad, and not thought he might have had a <hi>ſuperſedeas</hi> from this ſevere diſcipline of mortification?</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:100527:5"/>
            <p>He was now acquainted with Viſions and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations, he had been taken up into the third Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and there heard things unutterable. Who could have been partaker of thoſe exaltations, and not thought he had been exempted from the toil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom condition of warfaring men? But ſee here the excellency of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> temper: neither the ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his life, nor the labours of his calling, nor the greatneſs of his ſufferings, nor the height of his exaltations, nor the honor of his Divine Aſſumption could make him ſecure, nor puff him up with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of his own inconcuſſibility, but he remains a fighter ſtill. When <hi>Moſes</hi> came down from talking with God upon Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> It is ſaid the skin of his face ſhone, but he wiſt not of it. Though St. <hi>Pauls</hi> life ſo ſhined before men, that they might ſee the luſtre of his ſanctity; yet he himſelf wiſt not of it: for he ſaw not what he was, but what he was not; not what he had, but what he wanted; not how ſhort others came of him, but how ſhort himſelf came of the mark he aimed at. He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered not ſo much what height of Grace he had attained to, as what danger the higheſt degree was expoſed to; and ſo not contenting himſelf to have apprehended, but forgetting thoſe things, that were behind, he reached forth towards the things that were before, and preſſed towards the mark of the prize of the high calling of God in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:100527:6"/>
            <p>Hear this then, thou that liveſt in pleaſure and dwelleſt careleſly, that ſayeſt <hi>regina ſum,</hi> I am rich, and cloathed with Scarlet, that ſingeſt to thy ſoul the fools <hi>requiem,</hi> Soul take thy eaſe, thou haſt much Goods laid up for many years:</p>
            <p>That ſayeſt with them in St. <hi>Bernard, Sufficit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis, meliores eſſe nolumus,</hi> we have enough, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be no better. <hi>Quae inſania eſt, non quantum potes omnino facias cum neſcis penitus quid tibi ad ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſufficit?</hi> What a madneſs is it in thee, not to do all thou canſt for ſalvation, when thou knoweſt, when thou haſt done the moſt thou canſt, that the Righteous ſhall ſcarcely be ſaved? Art thou more holy than St. <hi>Paul?</hi> Did he after ſuch large acquiſitions in Chriſts Kingdom ſtill contend for more, and doſt thou content thy ſelf with a <hi>modi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum,</hi> a little upon a Knives point? Gid St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſtill hunger and thirſt after Righteouſneſs, and art thou ſatiate and cloyed with a little bit or moiſel? Had St. <hi>Paul</hi> done ſo much, and yet not ſure of the Crown? And doſt thou who haſt not done half ſo much, boaſt of thy aſſurance? Nay did St. <hi>Paul</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all this, fear leſt when he had Preached to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, he himſelf ſhould become a caſt-away? And doſt thou boaſt of thy Victory? Doſt not thou ſee, that the talleſt Trees are moſt expoſed to the violence of ſtorms and tempeſts, and the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt buildings to the injury of wind and weather? And doſt not thou know, that the higher our ſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100527:6"/>is in Grace, the more obnoxious we are to the Devils Temptations? For it grieves him (ſaith <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi>) to ſee in the Saints of God <hi>tot mortis opera di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruta, tot damnationis titulos eraſos, itaque obſervat, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnat, obſidet.</hi> He marks them, he aſſaults them, he beſiegeth them with the moſt exquiſite tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions he hath: knowing if he overthrows them, their falls will prove like falls of mighty Cedars, beating down a great company of lower ſhrubs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. And therefore be not high minded but fear, and work out your ſalvation with fear and trembling: conſidering we are not <hi>comprehenſores,</hi> comprehenſors, but <hi>viatores</hi> travellers; not <hi>in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triâ,</hi> our own Country, but <hi>in viâ</hi> upon our way thither; not <hi>in triumpho,</hi> but <hi>in militiâ,</hi> not in triumph but in warfare, <hi>&amp; quamdiu in certamine ſumus, nulla certa eſt victoria,</hi> as St. <hi>Jerom,</hi> ſo long as we are in the Combate, there is no victory certain. Let the ſame mind be in you, that was in St. <hi>Paul</hi> who for all his perfections, for all his ſanctity gave not over the ſtudy of mortification, <hi>I keep under my body,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I paſs to the ſecond part. The Antagoniſt he fights againſt, his body, <hi>corpus meum</hi> my body. The skill of a Souldier is tried by his adverſary. As St. <hi>Paul</hi> was an old Souldier of Chriſt, ſo he had many enemies to encounter in his Chriſtian warfare, but <hi>quae peſtis efficacior ad nocendum,
<note place="margin">Boctius.</note> quam familiaris inimicus?</hi> what plague is more
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100527:7"/>powerful to hurt a man, than a familiar enemy? And what more familiar, than a mans own body.</p>
            <p>But that we labour not of ambiguities, we muſt diſtinguiſh here betwixt <hi>concupiſcentiam corporis, &amp; ſubſtantiam corporis,</hi> the luſt of the body and the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the body. My body comprehends both, but principally the Luſt of the body, leſs principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Subſtance of the body.</p>
            <p>Principally (I ſay) the Luſt of the body. That there is concupiſcence remaining in the beſt Saints of God while they live here <hi>ad agonem, &amp; certamen,</hi> I ſuppoſe is a truth granted by all good Chriſtians. That that concupiſcence is an adverſary to us is in terms expreſſed by St. <hi>Paul.</hi> The fleſh luſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſpirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> v. 15. And by St. <hi>Peter, Dearly beloved, I beſeech you as pilgrims and ſtrangers abſtain from fleſhly luſts which war againſt the ſoul,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> ii. 11. And if it luſts againſt the ſpirit, and wars againſt the ſoul, 'tis an adverſary ſure, and a moſt dangerous adverſary too; becauſe it fights not <hi>propriis viribus,</hi> by its own ſtrength alone, but as a Confederate with the World and the Devil, it betrays us into their hands. <hi>The prince of this world cometh and hath nothing in me,</hi> ſaith our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>John</hi> xiv. 30. and therefore could do him no hurt: becauſe he had nothing in him to work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but when the Prince of this world cometh to us, he hath ſomthing in us to take part with him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us. And therefore he orders the matter ſo,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100527:7"/>that he tempts us not outwardly by word or ſign, nor immediately by himſelf, but moſt commonly by the mediation of the fleſh. As when he came to <hi>Eve,</hi> he hid himſelf in a creature, <hi>ut dolo homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſupplantaret, quem viribus nequiret,</hi> that he might overthrow her by fraud whom he could not by force: So when he comes to us he hides himſelf in the fleſh, and ſo much the more difficult he is to be reſiſted, <hi>quia interius oppugnans de nobis contra nos roboratur,</hi> as <hi>Lombard,</hi> becauſe he fighting with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us ſtrengthens himſelf of us againſt us. The Meſſenger that was ſent to buffet St. <hi>Paul,</hi> was <hi>ſtimulus in carne,</hi> a thorn in the fleſh. <hi>Leo</hi> calls the fleſh <hi>luſtrum Diaboli,</hi> the Devils Den. Another one <hi>vallum Diaboli,</hi> the Devils trench: becauſe by that the Devil fortifies himſelf againſt us. And is not the World it ſelf, that other Enemy of ours, aſſiſted by the luſts within? <hi>For all that is in the world, is the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> ii. 16. All the baits and ſnares the world does uſe to intrap us, could no us no hurt, were it not that the fleſh did luſt after them, and by the ſenſes as ſo many Cinqueports, and win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, let in the temptation.</p>
            <p>No marvel then St. <hi>Paul</hi> begins firſt with that, his fleſh and the luſts of it. The beſt way to be ſecure from the Enemy without the Walls, is to diſpatch the Traytor within. The beſt way to ſtrengthen our ſelves againſt a Foreign Enemy, is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100527:8"/>to weaken his Confederates at home. The Fleſh does not fight againſt the Soul it ſelf alone, but it is Confederate with the World and the Devil, in whoſe Territories their Caſtles and Fortifications ſtand: and therefore the beſt way to overcome them is to Mortifie the Luſts within: as St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine, Qui foris nos oppugnant intus vincimus, vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendo concupiſcentias, per quas nobis dominantur.</hi> They which aſſault us without, we overcome within, by overcoming our Luſts, by which they rule over us. One being asked therefore what was <hi>honeſtiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimum bellum,</hi> the honeſteſt war, anſwered, <hi>quod contra concupiſcentias carnis,</hi> which was made againſt the Luſts of the Fleſh; and that principally, no queſtion, St. <hi>Paul</hi> fought againſt.</p>
            <p>But the Body it ſelf, in ſome moderate ſenſe, for that is an Adverſary, in a reſpect ſubordinate, by reaſon of its Alliance, and Relation it hath to the Luſt within. For though inorditnae Luſt, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence be not only in the Body, but in the Soul alſo: yet you may obſerve in the Language of the Scriptures it takes the denomination chiefly from the Body; It is called the Fleſh, the Luſt of the Fleſh, our Earthly Members: and why ſo?</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe, though the Body be not the houſe alone where it dwells, yet it is the Shop wherein, as a Potter upon his Clay; it forms and frames the Idols of filthineſs, and puts them in execution;</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:100527:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Dum ſerpit in carne, in venis aeſtuat, intrat oſſa, conditur in medullis, fervet in ſanguine &amp; in vitiorum phreneſim ſic erumpit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſologus:</hi> It creeps in the Fleſh, it boils in the Veins, it enters the Bones, it is hid in the Marrow, it grows hot in the Bloud, and ſo breaks out into a phrenſie of wickedneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another Reaſon, why it takes the nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Body, is, becauſe thereby 'tis cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and maintained, <hi>nutriuntur cum carne, &amp; vitia carnis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> the Luſts of the Fleſh are nouriſhed with the Fleſh it ſelf. We know it by experience, when the Body is plyed, and forced with delicious Fare, when the Veins are full and the Bloud boils high, when Spirits are lively the Luſts within are kindled. If we be ſo happy as not to find it, yet God himſelf found it ſo amongſt his own people, <hi>Deut.</hi> xxxii. 15. <hi>When</hi> Jeſhurun <hi>waxed fat, he kicked,</hi> and <hi>Jer.</hi> v. 7.8. <hi>When I fed them to the full they were as fed horſes neighing after their neighbours wives.</hi> We ſee by the pampering of the Body the Luſts within were kindled; and to uſe the Body always too friendly is nothing elſe but to open a Shop wherein keen inſtruments are made to wound our own Souls. St. <hi>Baſil</hi> records of <hi>Plato,</hi> that conſidering of the great nocument that comes by too much indulging of the genius, he cauſed the Academy of <hi>Athens</hi> to be built in a very unhealthful place, that he might by that means cut off the too much proſperity of the body, as they do
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100527:9"/>luxuriant brances from the Vine. <hi>Plato</hi> was eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Divine Philoſopher, yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> was a greater Divine than he, for he being <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, taught of God, knew that the body of death within him, had ſuch Alliance to his mortal body without him: That if his Body were always rampant, his Luſt would be ſo too, to prevent which miſchief St. <hi>Paul</hi> kept a ſtrict regiment over his body. <hi>I keep under my body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I come to the third part, <hi>Modus pugnandi,</hi> the manner of his fighting, <hi>I keep it under.</hi> The word in the <hi>Greek</hi> is very Emphatical, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſignifies primarily, to ſtrike under the Eyes or on the Face, as Cuffers do, wherefore <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it, <hi>lividum facio,</hi> I make it black and blew-<hi>Beza</hi> renders it <hi>contundo.</hi> The vulgar <hi>Latine caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi> I chaſten it. Which Tranſlation ſoever we follow, two things are implyed in it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, St. <hi>Pauls</hi> earneſtneſs, and therefore he ſpeaks in oppoſition to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the skirmiſhing in ſport and paſtime, which went before the ſolemn fight, wherein they only beat the air and not their adverſary.</p>
            <p>Before the Combats of old, to which St. <hi>Paul</hi> here alludes, there were certain preparations uſed in jeſt to the ſolemn fight, by brandiſhing of the Weapon; whence came that phraſe in <hi>Seneca, aliud eſt ventilare, aliud pugnare;</hi> 'tis one thing to bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh the Weapons in the air, another thing to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100527:9"/>fight. Now St. <hi>Paul</hi> to ſhew that he was not in jeſt, but in earneſt, ſaith he did not beat the air but his body, directed his blows upon his adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. There are many in the world that do <hi>aerem verberare,</hi> beat the air with words and talk of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, that brandiſh their Weapons often in the air, yet when they come to uſe them, like the children of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> who being harneſſed, and carrying Bows gave back in the days of Battel. Fine Maſters, that as St. <hi>Jerom</hi> ſaith, <hi>pleno ventre diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putant de jejunio,</hi> diſpute of Faſting with full Bellies. St. <hi>Paul</hi> did not ſo, he ſhewed not what he could do, but did, what he ought to do, he beat not the air with boaſting and oſtentation, but he directs his blows upon his adverſary, not as beating the air, <hi>but I keep under my body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in the ſecond place, as the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> implies his earneſtneſs, ſo it does his auſterity in maceration of himſelf with ſome hard uſage, for he could not cuff his body, or beat it black and blew, nor chaſten it without ſome ſeverity uſed towards it.</p>
            <p>It ſeems then the Fleſh is not to be overcome with courteſie, and fair uſage, but ſome ſelf-ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation, and afflictions. As Medicines ſeldom cure the part affected, unleſs they put us to ſome grief and pain: no more do theſe afflictions of our ſelves unleſs they put the Body to ſome pain and grief. That Rule that <hi>Caligula</hi> would have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100527:10"/>by his bloudy Executioners, <hi>Ita feri ut ſentiat ſe mori,</hi> ſtrike him ſo, that he may perceive he dies; it is good to uſe ſomtimes in a holy ſeverity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ſelves, ſtrike our ſelves ſo, that we may perceive we dye. Let the ſenſe of pain be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the pleaſure we have taken in ſin. 'Tis not warm weather, or fair Sun-ſhine days; that kills the Vermin of the Earth; but Froſt and Snow and cold Winter ſtorms. 'Tis not the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring and ſparing of the Ground that deſtroys the Weeds and Bryars, but the rending Plow and Harrow that breaks up the Earth: ſo it is not the favourable and courteous uſing of the body, that ſubdue the Luſts of it: but the Plows and Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of mortification. 'Tis not every one that hath gotten dominion over his Luſts, but <hi>qui paſſus eſt in carne, he that hath ſuffered in the fleſh, hath ceaſed from ſin,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> iv. 1. Well then ſo far we are gone in the manner of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> fighting with the body, as to ſee it was managed with much earneſtneſs and ſeverity. But in particular what Weapons St. <hi>Paul</hi> uſed in this Combat with his Fleſh, or what we are to uſe when we enter the Liſts, yet we know not. And therefore as <hi>Gideon</hi> ſaid to the Angel, when he ſent him againſt the <hi>Midianites, obſecro, Domine mi; in quo?</hi> wherewith ſhall I go againſt them? So now it may be deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>obſecro, mi Domine, in quo?</hi> wherewith ſhall we fight againſt the Body? To make way for the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100527:10"/>demonſtration of that, I ſhall make ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions to you, and leave them to your conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p>What think you of <hi>Davids</hi> humiliation, lying upon the Ground, hard Lodging? <hi>And</hi> David <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted a faſt, and lay all night upon the earth,</hi> 2 Sam. xii. 16.</p>
            <p>What ſay you to <hi>Ahabs</hi> Sackcloth, and coarſe Clothing in the time of his humiliation? Though <hi>Ahab</hi> was a wicked King, yet his humiliation ſo far pleaſed God, that it turned away his judgments from him. <hi>Seeſt thou</hi> (ſaith the Lord to <hi>Eliah</hi>) <hi>how</hi> Ahab <hi>humbleth himſelf before me, becauſe he hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth himſelf before me,</hi> &amp;c. 1 <hi>King.</hi> xxi. 29. and how did <hi>Ahab</hi> humble himſelf before him ſee <hi>v.</hi> 27. <hi>And</hi> Ahab <hi>put on ſackcloth upon his fleſh, and faſted and lay in ſackcloth.</hi> But further, what think you of <hi>Timothies</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> drinking of water, for ſo tis certain he did till St. <hi>Paul</hi> relaxed the rigour of his diſcipline, <hi>Drink no longer water but a little wine, for thy ſtomachs ſake, and thy often infirmities,</hi> 1 Tim. v. 23. But theſe are all now antiquated, and out of uſe, and not likely to be retrieved. Well, therefore I urge them not, I preſs them not. But three things there are, that I muſt and will commend unto you, whether you hear or whether you will forbear, as fit means to be uſed for this purpoſe, becauſe we are ſure St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf uſed them in theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats with his body, for twice he makes mention of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100527:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>them in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> vi. 5. and Chap. xi. 27. In labours and watchings and faſtings. One good Weapon for the ſubduing of the Body, and the Luſts of it, is labour and diligent imployment in our lawful and honeſt calling: for <hi>omnis otioſus eſt in deſideriis</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Jerom</hi>) every idle man is luſtful. St. <hi>Paul</hi> took ſo much pains in planting of the Goſpel that he flew, (as St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſaith) all over the world, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Euſebius</hi> writeth of <hi>Origen,</hi> that <hi>ad corporis libidinem refraenandam non exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guos exantlavit labores,</hi> for the bridling of the Luſts he took great pains. And for this cauſe <hi>Caſsian</hi> writes, that the Monks in <hi>Egypt</hi> were not ſuffered to be idle, but they got their livings with their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. They ſaid one to another, <hi>non eſt viri ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorem timere,</hi> 'tis not for a man to fear the ſweat of his brows. And for this cauſe St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writ his Book, <hi>De opere Monachorum,</hi> of the labour of Monks. Sure I am, when theſe were laid aſide, given over in their Monaſteries, upon pretence of contemplation, and ſpeculation only; wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and filthineſs crept in at the gates of idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>The Fleſh loves eaſe, and idleneſs, and by idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs falls into luxury and wantonneſs. As <hi>Rome</hi> did when <hi>Carthage</hi> was deſtroyed, and <hi>Greece</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, for want of imployment abroad, they drowned themſelves in all kind of vices, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs at home. While <hi>David</hi> was imployed in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100527:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>his wars, we read of no inordinate Luſt that Reigned in him. While <hi>Solomon</hi> was imployed in building of the Temple, we read of no wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he fell into; but when he was idle at home, then his Eyes went after ſtrange women. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>onus aſino,</hi> lay a burden upon the Aſs and he will leave kicking. That Counſel that the Wiſeman gave, <hi>Ecclus.</hi> xxxiii. 26, 27. concerning an evil ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, is good to be uſed towards the body at ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time. A Yoak and a Collar bow down the neck, ſo do torments an evil ſervant, ſend him to labour, that he be not idle, ſet him into work as is fit for him. If he be not obedient, lay on him more heavy Fetters.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Weapon for the ſubduing of the Fleſh is Watching, riſing in the night to Praytr, and Holy Reading, breaking of our ſleep ſomtimes for Devotion. St. <hi>Paul</hi> was not only in labours but in watching, nay in watching often. <hi>Euſeb.</hi> ſaith of <hi>Origen,</hi> That as in the day-time he took great pains in the ſtudy of Divine Learning, ſo he ſpent great part of the night in ſo doing. And <hi>Socrates</hi> of one <hi>Macarius</hi> a holy man, that giving inſtructions to one about continence, told him that <hi>nunquam cepit ſomnum ad ſatietatem,</hi> he never ſlept to ſatiety for the ſpace of twenty years. The fleſh like the ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard in the <hi>Proverbs</hi> is ever craving a little ſleep, a little ſlumber, a little folding of the hands, and give it what it craves, it grows unruly. St. <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:100527:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>exhorts the <hi>Romans,</hi> Chap. xiii. <hi>To walk honeſtly as in the day, not in Chambering, and Wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> joyns here Wantonneſs <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> lying in Bed, and they commonly go together, or fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low one another. The beginning of Concupiſcence is that in the fourth of <hi>Amos, They ſtretch themſelves upon their beds.</hi> If thy Enemy grow too ſtrong for thee, the weapon of watching is good to ſubdue him. <hi>Suetonius</hi> records of <hi>Caligula</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, that when he was about to make an Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he would threaten ſomtimes, <hi>ſtricturum ſe lucu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brationis ſuae telum,</hi> he would draw the weapon of his night watchings. O if thy Luſt do infeſt thee, do but draw <hi>vigiliarum telum,</hi> the weapon of thy night Prayers, and that will curb it. <hi>Watch and Pray that ye enter not into temptation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third weapon to be uſed in theſe Combats with the Fleſh is Faſting. St. <hi>Paul</hi> was not only in Labours, and Watchings, but in Faſtings too. The Fleſh is <hi>moleſtus cliens,</hi> a troubleſom client ever crying <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, let me not be hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, let me not be dry. Now to hold it to <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaius</hi> commons, <hi>modicum panis, &amp; pauxillum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quae,</hi> a little bread, and a little water, will grieve it much and afflict it; and therefore all the Saints of God made uſe of it, in their Combats with the Fleſh, but <hi>David</hi> of all others was moſt dextrous at this Weapon. <hi>I chaſtned my ſoul with faſting,</hi> Pſalm xxxv. <hi>my knees grow weak through faſting.</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:100527:12"/>And St. <hi>Jerom</hi> records of <hi>Hilarion,</hi> that old <hi>Aſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick,</hi> that if any time he found any mutining of his Luſts, he would threaten, <hi>fame te conficiam, &amp; ſtti.</hi> I will wound thee with hunger and thirſt. This was the weapon, that all the old Soldiers of Chriſt were famous at, who lived and dyed in the Holy Wars of Chriſt, that I may ſay of that as <hi>David</hi> did of <hi>Goliahs</hi> ſword, <hi>There is none to that.</hi> The firſt dart that ever the Devil flung at the ſoul of man, was by Gluttony, <hi>primum Diaboli ſpiculum,</hi> and one weapon God hath given us to wound that body of ſin is Faſting. Faſting nails the Fleſh to the Croſs of Chriſt. Faſting tames the frankneſs of Nature. Faſting ſubdues the rebellion of Luſt. Faſting overthrows the fortifications of <hi>Satan,</hi> and undermines the Palaces of Wantonneſs, ſo there is none to that, take it abſtractly, but in conjunction with the other two excellent means for keeping the body under.</p>
            <p>But it may be objected againſt the uſe of theſe out of <hi>Epheſ.</hi> v. 29. <hi>No man ever yet hated his own fleſh, but loveth and cheriſheth it, even as Chriſt his Church.</hi> By uſing of theſe diſciplines over our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, we ſhall hate our own Fleſh.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, all caſtigation, and affliction is not an effect of hatred, ſome proceeds of love. A Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chaſtens his Son, yet loves him ſtill, Chriſt chaſtens his Church, yet loves her well; whom God loves, he chaſteneth. I hope St. <hi>Paul</hi> did not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100527:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>hate the inceſtous <hi>Corinthian,</hi> when he delivered him unto <hi>Satan</hi> for the deſtruction of his Fleſh, that his Soul might be ſaved in the day of the Lord, much leſs do we hate the Fleſh, when we chaſten it ſo, that our Soul may be ſaved in the day of the Lord. 'Tis a good Apology that St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> makes for thoſe <hi>Aſceticks</hi> in his time, <hi>Non enimcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus ſuum, ſed corruptiones, &amp; pondus oderunt,</hi> they don't hate their bodies, but the corruptions of them, and afterwards, when they ſeem by Continence, and Labours to perſecute their bodies they do it not that they may have no bodies, but that they may have their bodies ſubjugated and ready to every good work.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is further objected that this diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline ſmells of Superſtition. St. <hi>Paul</hi> condemns <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> not ſparing of the body for a piece of ſuperſtition, <hi>Col.</hi> ii. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> iv. 8. he op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> this bodily exerciſe to Godlineſs, and ſaith, it profiteth little.</p>
            <p>I anſwer 'tis true, but St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh not of all afflictions of the body, nor all bodily exerciſe, for then he ſhould condemn his own practice in the Text, but he means ſuch affliction of the body, as is without knowledg, and moderation. And if this bodily exerciſe be uſed without knowledg of the right uſe, and end of it, making it a part of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, meritorious of Salvation, a thing that does pleaſe God, <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100527:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>aim or reſpect, then they are not excuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>Or Secondly, if it be uſed without moderation ſo as to deſtroy nature. As thoſe <hi>flagellantes in He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truria</hi> of whom <hi>Hoſpinian</hi> writes, that they wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring up and down openly cut themſelves with Cords and Whips, and kept a bloudy Feſtival for the ſpace of thirty three days, and then thought their ſins to be expiated, and themſelves reconciled unto God. And thoſe Monks of <hi>Palaeſtina</hi> of whom <hi>Evagrius</hi> writes, that they faſted ſomtime five whole days, and ſo afflicted themſelves with their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſupererogations of watchings, and labours, that they lay upon the ground, as dead men unburied.</p>
            <p>Theſe were immoderate in diſcreet afflictions, and ſo to be condemned. But yet as <hi>Zanchy</hi> upon the ſecond of the <hi>Coloſsians, Exercitia haec per ſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probari non poſſunt, circumſtantiae hae omnia damnant.</hi> Theſe exerciſes can be diſliked in themſelves, 'tis their circumſtances that ſpoil all: for as he alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Theſe bodily exerciſes are good, if they be with knowledg of the right uſe and end of them, and ſuch moderation as they deſtroy not nature, nor make it unſerviceable to the Soul. In themſelves they are lawful and laudable, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the word of God, and the practice of the Saints of God in the pureſt times. They are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100527:14"/>too, as for mortification of the Fleſh, ſo alſo for other excellent ends.</p>
            <p>As firſt, the Elevation of the Soul, and ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the mind to Heavenly Meditation. <hi>Tanto enim glorioſius mens ad ſuperiora fertur, quanto dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentius ab inferioribus concupiſcentia cohibetur,</hi> The Soul does advance more gloriouſly toward Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly things, when the Concupiſcence is moſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently kept from earthly things.
<note place="margin">D. Aug. de opere Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nachorum.</note> 
               <hi>Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas carnis vigorem mentis exacuit,</hi> The infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of the Fleſh does ſharpen the vigour of the mind. That therefore the ſtrength of the body may paſs into the virtues of the Soul, <hi>non tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pibus flammis medullae aeſtuant,</hi> &amp;c. Let not the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row boil with filthy flames, let not the hidden incentives ſet the Soul on fire, let not the wandring ſenſe wantoniſe the enjoyment of various delights, thoſe hinder the comforts, and refreſhments of the Soul, and quench the flame of ſpiritual conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Soul is never better devoted to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly things, then when the body is eſtranged from carnal pleaſure. <hi>Whom ſhall he teach knowledg? whom ſhall he make to underſtand doctrine? them that are weaned from the milk and from the breaſts,</hi> Iſa. xxviii. 9.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Moderate afflictions of the body, as they ſerve to diſpoſe the mind for Heavenly flights: ſo they are profitable to amerce our ſelves for our ſins in Repentance. Amongſt other fruits of Godly ſorrow St. <hi>Paul</hi> reckons up indignation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100527:14"/>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> vii. 11. 'tis not poſſible ſaith <hi>Calvin, quin anima Divini judicii horrore percuſſa, partes ultionis in exigendâ de ſe poenâ occupet,</hi> that the Soul being ſtricken with the horrour of Gods judgment, but it muſt take ſome revenge upon it ſelf by ſome puniſhment; And reaſon requires, that as the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy hath been partaker with the ſoul in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſin, ſo it ſhould partake of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the Soul in Repentance for ſin; and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we are to judg our ſelves in Repentance to prevent the judgment of God, good reaſon we ſhould judg our ſelves impartially, ſeverely, and ſo as it may be as God himſelf will judg us.</p>
            <p>Now 'tis his rule, <hi>quantum glorificavit ſe, tantum date illi tormentum,</hi> ſo much as ſhe hath glorified her ſelf, give her ſo much torment. To macerate then the fleſh in ſome degree; is but Righteous judgment. You may relie upon <hi>Calvins</hi> judgment in this, <hi>quia ſeveriores in nos ſumus, eò debemus ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare magis propitium Deum,</hi> The more ſevere we are to our ſelves, the more propitious we ought to hope God will be to us.</p>
            <p>And therefore though we favour not thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreet and immoderate afflictions of the body that have heretofore been uſed by ſome <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, and that are now in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, yet we are ſorry there is in the world ſuch general diſlike of the diſcipline of Mortification, that was uſed by the Apoſtles themſelves and holy
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100527:15"/>Chriſtians in the pureſt times. To ſee that men are grown ſuch lovers of themſelves that they will endure nothing againſt their eaſe, and pleaſure, to ſee the extremity of ſuch fooliſh zeal that to avoid that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> not ſparing of the body, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> toucheth upon, they directly run into that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that wantonneſs of the body, that all Chriſtianity condemns. That to avoid that ſuperſtition they underſtand not, they run counter upon his practice they do underſtand and ought to follow. To avoid the ſuſpicion of being <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> abſtemious, they turn plain <hi>Borborites</hi> wallowing in all Carnal Luſts and Pleaſures. To avoid the danger of ſymboliſing with the Papiſts, they run with the Heathen into all exceſs of riot. And as we are ſorry to ſee theſe things, ſo we are bold to open our mouths wide in this ſolemn aſſembly, and complain of it, as one cauſe of the grand impiety, lewdneſs and debauchery of theſe times. That men on Faſting days, Ember weeks, and the time of Lent, when they ſhould go to <hi>Joels</hi> doctrine of turning to the Lord with faſting, and weeping and mourning, they go to <hi>Jaels</hi> Butter and Milk in a Lordly diſh, wrap them warm, and lay them down and take their reſt; that they turn their faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing days into feaſting days; inſtead of watching in night to Prayer, ſleep away all Prayers in the day; inſtead of taking of revenge on themſelves for their ſins, let no pleaſure of the Spring paſs by
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100527:15"/>them. Men have found out an eaſier way of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to heaven then St. <hi>Paul</hi> knew, or the Saints in after ages, they can go now <hi>à deliciis ad delicias</hi> from the pleaſures of this world, to the pleaſures of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when the Church calls to lamentation and mourning, behold joy and gladneſs, ſlaying Oxen, and killing Sheep, eating fleſh and drinking Wine. <hi>Let us eat and drink for to morrow we ſhall die,</hi> Iſai. xxii. 12. That what <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Book <hi>Contra Pſychicos</hi> invidiouſly ſpake of the Orthodox. <hi>Quorum charitas in cacabis, quorum ſpes in ferculis, quorum fides in culinis,</hi> &amp;c. whoſe Charity is in their Boilers, whoſe Hope is in their Diſhes, whoſe Faith is in their Kitchin, whoſe Dreſſers are their Altars, whoſe Cooks are their Prieſts, whoſe God is their Belly: What St. <hi>Jerom</hi> was wont to ſay of his Country where he was born, <hi>In patria mea Deus venter eſt.</hi> In my Country every man makes his Belly his God. And what Sir <hi>Edwin Sands</hi> ſaith of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church in his <hi>Europae Speculum, That for a man, who were deſirous to ſave his Soul when he dyes, and yet deny himſelf no pleaſure while he lives, there is no ſuch Church as the</hi> Roman <hi>is,</hi> I fear me, may be ſpoken of ours in regard of our practice, Nay 'tis ſpoken by them in effect. They call us the locuſts in the Revelation; our ſong is <hi>eſca ventri,</hi> and <hi>venter eſcae,</hi> we live by the Fleſh Pots of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and by the Fleſh Pots of <hi>Egypt</hi> we will die, we live by the graves of luſt, and by the graves of luſt we will be buried.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:100527:16"/>
            <p>Suffer therefore a word of Exhortation, and 'tis but the word of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Tymothy.</hi> Suffer hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as good Soldiers: and that of St. <hi>James,</hi> Be afflicted and mourn, let your laughter be turned into mourning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe Auſterities I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to you are neither Popiſh, nor Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, they were practiſed by St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, the great Apoſtle. And if we will be Criſtians indeed we muſt be <hi>Paulianiſts</hi> in this point, be followers of him, even as he is of Chriſt. Let not the popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar clamours affright you from theſe underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, alas they ſpeak evil of thoſe things they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not. Let not the fears of weakneſs deter you. <hi>Ideò ſancti viri infirmiores ſe eſſe faciunt, quia ſi fortes, ſancti vix eſſe poſſunt,</hi> Therefore Holy men make themſelves weak, becauſe if luſty, they cannot be Holy. Let not the fear of pain, and ſuffering retard you. <hi>Noluit Deus hominem ad im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalem beatitudinem delicato itinere pervenire,</hi> God would not have men come to everlaſting bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in a way ſtrown with Roſes. And yet there is no ſuch bitterneſs in the matter, but will be recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed abundantly by the uſing of it. What St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of Gods chaſtiſements, I may ſay of theſe, and with that conclude this part of my Text. No chaſtning for the preſent ſeems joyous, neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs afterwards it brings forth the peaceable fruits of Righteouſneſs unto them which are exerciſed thereby.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:100527:16"/>
            <p>In now com to the fourth, and laſt part of my Text, the victory of St. <hi>Paul</hi> got by this manner of fighting <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I bring my body into ſubjection. In the word before St. <hi>Paul</hi> alludes to the cuffers, here he alludes to the wraſtlers in the <hi>Graecian</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats. The wraſtler that could by art, or force op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs his adverſary, and get him down, had the title of a <hi>Pancratiaſt,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Pancratiaſt</hi> was St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who by blows and hard uſage oppreſſed his body, and brought it into ſubjection. 'Tis not enough to Combat with the Fleſh, and the Luſts of it, there is a victory to be obtained. The Fleſh is ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of Rule and Dominion, and for that purpoſe as <hi>Semiramis</hi> did <hi>mentiri ſexum,</hi> belie her Sex that ſhe might get into the Throne of her Son <hi>Ninus,</hi> ſo the Fleſh and the Luſts of it do <hi>mentiri ſexum,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to Liberty, Zeal, and Conſcience; and if by any means it gets into the Throne, there is no Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant more Tyrannical, no brute more brutiſh, nor fury more furious, than the Luſts reigning, witneſs the fearful Tragedies acted in every Age, in every part of the World. As therefore God or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained that man ſhould rule over the woman, <hi>Gen.</hi> iii. 16. ſo <hi>Gen.</hi> iv. 7. he hath ordained that man ſhould rule over his Concupiſcence. His deſire ſhall be to thee, and thou ſhalt rule over him. The Pronoun <hi>him,</hi> and <hi>his,</hi> may refer to ſin, as the antecedent, and be rendered thus, Under thee ſhall the deſire of ſin be, and thou ſhalt rule over it,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100527:17"/>and Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf grants this to be as commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and agreeable to the Grammatical ſenſe as the other, Under thee ſhall his deſire be, and thou ſhalt rule over him.</p>
            <p>In Philoſophy they tell us, that the inferiour part is naturally apt to obey the ſuperiour, and the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour to govern the inferiour, though in the fall the ſouls of men received ſuch wounds and bruiſes, that the Reaſon does not now govern the Senſuali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>imperio deſpotico,</hi> as a Maſter governs his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, but <hi>imperio politico,</hi> as a Magiſtrate governs his people, which oftentimes fall into Seditions and Mutinies againſt him.</p>
            <p>But in Chriſtian Philoſophy we are taught by our Lord and Saviour Chriſt. <hi>Matth.</hi> xix. 12. That there be Eunuchs, which have made themſelves Eunuchs for the Kingdom of Heavens ſake. And how can any make themſelves Eunuchs without ſubjugation of their bodies, bringing their bodies in ſubjection. St. <hi>Paul</hi> does command all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to mortifie their earthly members, and evil Concupiſcence, and how can they mortifie their Concupiſcence, and make it dead, unleſs they rule over it. St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his Book againſt <hi>Juli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> the <hi>Pelagian,</hi> having diſcourſed largely of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, and the evil of it, yet at laſt ſaith, It is <hi>ſub poteſtate animae,</hi> under the power of the ſoul by the Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>in corpore mortis caſtiganda,</hi> in the body of death to be cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100527:17"/>and if it were not, how could St. <hi>Paul</hi> in truth proclaim it to the world that he had made ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment of it, and done it? The Chymiſts talk much of the Philoſophers ſtone, but they never ſhew it. St. <hi>Paul</hi> uſeth no Rodomontadoes in commendation of his Art, but propounds the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of it in his own example, as a great Aſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick. And the only Artifice whereby the Holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle did all this, was the abridging of himſelf the uſe of his Chriſtian Liberty: whereas he as a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an had a liberty to uſe all indifferent things freely, yet he would not uſe his liberty, he wrought with his hands, watched, faſted, and uſed many hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, he needed not to have done: whereby we ſee Chriſtian Liberty conſiſts not in a free uſe of all indifferent things, but in a perſuaſion of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, all things are lawful. <hi>All things are lawful for me, but all things are not expedient for me,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> vi. 12, 13. Though we have liberty to eat all kind of meats, yet we muſt uſe this liberty ſo, as ſtill to keep the body in ſubordination to the Spirit, that we may be able to deny our ſelves a lawful pleaſure when any thing makes it more expedient, as it is when the Church requires us ſomtimes to faſt for the humiliation of our ſouls and the ſubjugation of our bodies. 'Tis a memorable reſolution of our great Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> viii. <hi>ult.</hi> verſe, <hi>If meat make my brother to offend, I will eat no fleſh ſo long as the world ſtands.</hi> Is it lawful for St. <hi>Paul</hi> to renounce
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100527:18"/>the eating of fleſh ſo long as the world ſtands, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the ſcandal of one weak brother, and is it not lawful for a Chriſtian to forbear the eating of fleſh for a time to avoid the ſcandal of his Superiours? I would fain know in matter of ſcandal, whether it be a greater offence to go againſt the judgment of ſome weak and ignorant man, by aſſed only by his own fancy and prejudice, than againſt the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the whole Church, wherein there are ſo many wiſe, and holy men, and they backed by the Authority of an Eſtabliſhed Law? Well then ſeeing ſome faſting is <hi>ſub praecepto,</hi> under a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand not only of God but of the Church alſo, that <hi>in caſu ſcandali,</hi> we are not to infringe the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Magiſtrate to gratifie the humour of ſome ignorant Chriſtians. It would be our wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to ſhew our affections and obedience to the Church, whereof we are members, and in ſome meaſure to conform our ſelves to the Laws of faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that are there in force. I conclude with that excellent Counſel of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet</hi> ii. 16. <hi>As free and not uſing your liberty as a cloak of maliciouſneſs.</hi> In which words there are two things obvious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, <hi>as free,</hi> and then a caution, <hi>not uſing your liberty as a cloak of maliciouſneſs.</hi> All Chriſtians are made partakers of a glorious liberty by Chriſt, no queſtion, but then here is a caution, not uſing their liberty as an occaſion to the fleſh, which they do undoubtedly, whenſoever they confront the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100527:18"/>juſt Laws of the Church, whereof the King is Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Governor, and fall foul upon that Law, 13, 14. Verſes, to which the Counſel of St. <hi>Peter</hi> is ſubſervient, <hi>They uſe their liberty as a cloak of mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
